welcome this is math 676 my name is
Wolfgang bangers I'm a professor in the
math department at Texas A&M and what I
would like to talk about in this class
and over the course of the semester is
about finite element methods in
scientific computing scientific
computing is a very broad field
it involves modeling and representing
the world in terms of computer programs
and predicting things that we cannot
let's say predict just intuitively and
one of the biggest methods in scientific
computing is to find an element method
so what I would like to do in this
semester is take a broad view of
scientific computing I would like to
introduce you to the finite element
method I would like to introduce you to
the tools that we use to represent the
finite element method on computers but I
would also like to introduce you to
let's say common approaches to
discretizing finite element
discretization partial differential
equations was the final element methods
what to do with linear systems that come
out of this and so on and so forth so
it's going to be a class that is fairly
broad that involves a little bit of
theory that involves a lot of
programming that involves a lot of
knowledge that let's say gives you a
bigger view of this field and in
particular one of the things that I
would like to do is I would like to
introduce you to some of the existing
software packages that exist out of
their idea
so in scientific computing what you
often encounter is that you need to
solve let's say real problems not just
model problems for example that applies
equation on the unit square but that you
want to solve things that are
uncomplicated geometries in 3d or that
require multi grid solvers or they
require higher water methods and so on
and so forth and it will turn out to be
rather difficult to implement all of
these things in a code from scratch
and so my goal in this class is among
other things that
to use you to the libraries that are out
there that you can use for this and
specifically to one of the libraries
that implement the finite element
methods and that is a library that I and
as it's around the world implement or
develop that is called deal tuned so let
me start with a little bit of an
overview of this class and a rationale
for why we would want to consider as
your libraries so the topic of this
class like I said was to learn how to
solve differential equations on
computers in particular using the finite
element method as a as an example you
will sometimes hear me say that I
consider to find a difference method or
to find a volume method these are the
two other big methods for partial
differential equations as essentially
equivalent to the finite element method
and I think that is generally true that
most of the finer difference in most of
the finite volume methods today can be
written as variance or as perturbations
of finite element methods so I consider
this finite element method as let say an
overview of a broader class that
contains the attitude so from a
practical perspective partial
differential in partial differential
equations on computers is a very
practical field it is not so much
concerned with writing down equations
and analyzing them very carefully on a
piece of paper but it has a lot to do
with interacting with people from
applied fields so you work with people
from nuclear engineering or from
aerospace or from biomedical imaging or
from the geosciences and what they often
have is that they have equations that
need to be solved somehow and so the
role of computational science or
scientific computing oftentimes is to
take the equations as they come whether
they're pleasant to solve or not which
are easy or difficult doesn't really
matter that much because we need to
solve them because there's an
application and so if you want to do
this you need to have knowledge in a
very broad class of fields so you need
to know something about partial
differential equations and how to behave
viii you need to know a lot about
discretization so that means converting
an infinite dimensional partial
differential equation into a finite
dimensional problem you need to know
something about the linear solvers and
preconditioners that involved in this
but then you also need to have a
background in programming and oftentimes
programming with very large software
pieces often times sours and tens of
thousands maybe hundreds of thousands of
lines of code and so for this you need
to know adequate tools you just can't
deal with software at this magnitude
anymore if all you know is let's say a
simple editor for example and there are
very good tools for these sort of things
out there so this course math 676 will
cover all of these to some degree I
won't have lectures that talk about
let's say the character of differential
equations that talk about different
kinds of discretization and we'll talk
about solvers and preconditioners there
will be a lot about how to program how
to avoid bugs how to debug things and
there will be several lectures about
adequate tools so I will introduce you
to what we call integrated development
environments IDs deserve let's say
programming environments that will
introduce you to tools for visualization
that will introduce you to tools for
documenting codes for examples so this
is the the field of scientific computing
broadly construed and that is the goal
of this class that I introduce you into
all of these aspects so broadly speaking
the goals of this class is to introduce
you to widely used methods in scientific
computing in particular using this
software called DL - that's the software
library that supports finding element
computations I will show you in quite
some detail how to use geo - in practice
I will introduce you to let's say how do
you write code how do you write programs
based on DL - how may be a little bit
also how internally these sort of things
are represented but then I will also
show you modern software development
tools and I will teach you a little bit
about so from a development practice
I think these are very applicable topics
that certainly don't just pertain to
academics or like me who work as
professors but these are all things that
are very important also for practical
applications in industry in the National
Labs in many other fields as well things
are not goals of this class are that I'm
not going to introduce you to the finite
element method itself in particular I'm
not going to talk about the mathematical
basis for it that is something that I
expect you to have heard in a class
before or that you have acquired through
reading literature similarly I'm not
going to show you with the exception of
one single lecture where I'm going to
talk about templates not going to show
you how to program in C++ expect that
you already know how to program in C++
and if you don't it would be worthwhile
to take a short course on this or to
take one of the existing books on C++ if
you struggle with these sort of concepts
here are a number of books that I
typically recommend so from a
mathematical perspective to the book by
Zhu Brenner and Ridgway Scott about the
mathematical theory of finite element
methods is sort of the standard book
from for mathematicians it is not
written for engineers for sure but it
lays out the theory of finite elements
in their analysis there is a book by DJ
plays originally from in German but
translated into English that's called
just finite elements that gives you
let's say it's slightly more applied
overview of this of this of the finite
element method it is not by any stretch
and engineering introduction to this but
I think it is a little bit more let's
say accessible if you're not a
mathematician as far as for C++ these
standard work is by be honest draw
stroke it's called the C++ programming
language we are in Strasbourg
incidentally is a
we're in the computer science department
here at the same University at Texas A&M
just over there and in one of the
buildings here on campus he is the
inventor of C++ or let's say the person
who originally came up with it in the
late 1970's and early 1980s and of
course in the mean time in the 30 years
since then a lot of people have
contributed to it but he is still the
one whose book is let's say the standard
reference on C++ and is well written is
certainly a book worth reading if you
are not accounted familiar with C++ yet
so let me motivate a little bit one of
the big themes of this class namely that
we want to use existing approaches and
in particular existing software in this
class to solve the problems that come
out of the Applied Sciences so let me
start with partial differential
equations of course PDEs appear in all
sorts of applications there is of course
the let's say classical applications and
structural statics and dynamics for
example if you want to investigate the
deformation of a bridge as a truck
drives over it or let's say how a road
deforms if a truck is on it how a car
deforms if it impacts it as a car or
maybe how a carb deforms as it is
subjected to the load from the air that
passes it these are all described as
PDEs
similarly in fluid dynamics you can ask
the question for example how does the
water flow around a ship
how does air flow around a car or in an
airfoil fluid dynamics also plays a role
for example in pipe networks for example
in oil pipelines then PDEs are also used
in aerodynamics flow around cars
airplanes rockets and so on so forth and
so now I've given you the the three
basic states of matter namely solid
fluid
and gasps of course PDS also play a role
in the fourth state of matter in plasma
dynamics for example in astrophysics or
when you want to investigate fusion
energy these are described by PDEs
typically that these are sort of the
classical applications of partial
differential equations but PDEs appear
in many other areas that you don't
immediately think of for example in
biology people use PDEs to model how
bacteria migrate towards a food source
for example or maybe away from areas
where there's too many bacteria already
people also use PD is to model financial
instruments for example in the 1990s the
Nobel Prize for economics went to two
people called blacks and Scholz who
found out that you can describe the cost
or the price that you should ask for
stock options using an equation that
today we call the black scores equation
that's a partial differential equation
and then you can apply PDEs to
epidemiology to practically every area
you can think of so PDEs are used in a
really wide variety of areas and what
then the role of computational sciences
is to take these equations and solve
them whatever the people from the
Applied Sciences give to you this is
what you want to solve and so the goal
of this class is to introduce you to
give you a little bit of an overview of
PDS
and then how you would approach solving
them so let's say you somebody gives you
an equation and you need to write the
software that solves this then there are
essentially two approaches either you
can take a software that already solves
this or you can write it yourself for
many applications in particular the ones
that are listed at the top here there is
standard software out there that's
commercially available that that solves
these sort of problems so there is
software that
certainly solves for the elastic
deformation of structures there is
certainly software for air and water
flow and so on and so forth so in these
sort of cases there is not much for you
to do you should of course use
professionally written software that
solves whatever application you have but
there are two cases where you have to
write software yourself namely wait if
you're somebody who develops
computational methods like me for
example then there is by definition no
commercial software out there that
already does that my goal is to develop
numerical methods that are better than
the ones that are used in the past or
that have been used in the past and so
as a consequence I cannot use commercial
software because that by definition does
not use the sort of modern methods that
I'm interested in the other area where
you have to write your own software is
when you have a non-standard problem so
if a biologist comes to you and says I
want to simulate how bacteria move on my
petri dish then that would be the sort
of application where you cannot find
commercial software it's just too small
a niche market nobody cares about this
enough to write a program that might
cost a million dollars to develop a more
when there's only ten people in the
world who care about this particular
application or who let's say who care
about simulating this on a computer and
so in these sort of cases you have a
non-standard problem you need to write
your own solvers so if you encounter one
of these two cases either new methods or
non-standard problems you have three
different choices either you write
something from scratch yourself or you
build something from existing components
so you take a library that gives you
building blocks for example and you put
it together and the third one would be
you start with an application that
solves something similar and you
modified the point I want to make in the
rest of this lecture essentially is that
option one should not be your choice
because it might either be very
difficult or it might be time-consuming
or expensive and I think at least for
people like me in mathematics we often
have it
tendency to still go with option number
one because we say we want to control
every possible variable we want to
really understand what's going on but
the argument that that I think I want to
make it is part of this class is that we
should really not do this because it
essentially means that we spend our
years of let's say as a graduate student
or as a researcher reinventing the wheel
far too many times
rather what we should be doing is we
should build on existing components or
if there is something that does
something similar already we should just
adapt it so because this is too abstract
I would like to give you a little bit of
an example of why I think that it's
worthwhile to build on something
existing so if you look at the three the
three standard tools for the numerical
solution of PDE is this would be the
finite element find a volume or find a
difference method basically all of them
have to do a number of steps so the
first thing is that you replace your
domain on which you want to solve this
PDE by a mesh into it let's say a set of
cells that we call a mesh or a
triangulation these measures can be
fairly complicated so on the right here
for example is an example of a measure
of a often underground reservoir so
these measures can have tens of
thousands of cells hundreds of thousands
maybe millions or even more and they can
have very complicated geometries so just
to represent meshes and to create these
meshes is certainly no simple task in
realistic applications then by and large
the way you can see partial differential
equations is or let's say a disco times
partial differential equation on a mesh
is that you have to define balance
relations essentially let's say if you
think of flow problems for example the
balance relationship it would be
whatever flows out of a cell must flow
in on the other side so most of the PDEs
that we write essentially come from
these sort of balanced relationships and
then when you have these balanced
relationships between cells you obtain
the typically very large
or a non-linear system that you have to
store and solve now every code that has
to do with solving numerical or
numerically solving PDEs has to has to
do these steps there's no way around it
and if you are tasked with coming up
with a code that does this for a
particular PDE you will realize of
course very quickly that you have only
so much time in a day to do this and as
a matter of fact you probably also have
only so much expertise maybe you're in a
an application scientists who know
everything knows everything about
subsurface flow but you're not
completely familiar let's say with
algebraic multigrid or with how to
define higher order shape functions and
so on and so forth and so if you wanted
to use modern numerical methods it would
be quite a steep learning curve to come
up with a code that shows all of these
things in let's say in it's full
complexity today so what I would like to
argue then is because of these
restrictions that it's worthwhile to
look into into existing libraries in
particular because we don't just want to
use methods that have been around for 30
years for example but we want to use
something that is state-of-the-art so
typically what I would consider
state-of-the-art in numerical PD
yesterdays for example that you want to
use adaptive measures that you want to
use realistic complex geometries higher
order elements multi grid solvers that
this whole thing should scale to let's
say thousands of processors on modern
hardware and that you want to get output
that is suitable for high quality
rendering and if you see this list of
course you should ask yourself well how
is it possible to make us have them in a
single code that is certainly going to
take years to implement this and it is
true that if you wanted to implement
this from scratch yes it would take
years
to me the question whether just as
possible or not it's not a question of
feasibility but it is a question of how
we develop software so we can ask a
question for example should every
student develop their own finite element
solver
we're sure to be reusing what others
have done in the past do we insist on
implementing things from scratch or do
we build an existing libraries and I
guess you can already figure what my
answers for this should be I think we
should reuse what others have done and
as a matter of fact there has been quite
a shift over the last 10 or 15 years in
this regard where in the past we sort of
certainly in the community that develops
numerical methods we thought that we
should just look at model problems and
implement things from scratch this has
changed I think that today we believe
that we should be reusing what others
have done because it gives us a better
handle on let's say you only wanted to
deal with the discretization but you can
still reuse a modern numerical solver
for the linear system that others have
come up with nevertheless there's there
is quite some let's say resistance to
this idea of reusing libraries and what
I would like to do in the next few
slides is that I go through some of the
arguments that people have made in the
past against reusing what others have
done I would like to talk about the
reasons for this so um let me actually
before I say too so just as an as an
introduction to existing software there
are a number of libraries that will
bring up repeatedly in this class so for
basic linear algebra the libraries that
exist is blast it's a basic linear
algebra subsystem or subroutines and
lapack for let's say higher order things
like computing eigenvectors and
eigenvalues of dense matrices then
there's it the next higher level would
be two libraries that are called Petzi
and rellenos that represent vectors in
sparse matrices solvers
of both of these support parallel
computations and then based on this we
build libraries like deal to the library
that I'm going to talk about in this
class that that do all of the meshing
and the finite element parts of this all
right so to come back to the arguments
that people have made against using
existing libraries and one of the things
that I'm often hear is that in order to
use somebody else's software of course
you have to learn the conventions that
are used in there how it works I need to
read through the documentation and
people say I'd be much faster if I just
wrote all of this myself because really
I only want to solve the Laplace
equation on unit squared and I think the
first part is certainly true you have to
learn a piece of software you have to
learn the philosophy that's behind us
but the second part is not true that
you're faster by writing the code
yourself because today in these
libraries that are just introduced to
you on the previous slide is that there
is so much functionality in there you
know hundreds of thousands of lines of
code that you can use that you don't
have to implement yourself and to just
give you an example of this if you think
about how today we use MATLAB where we
just plug and play and we put things
together and it all works we can write
code so fast in MATLAB today that the
maybe they're a little bit slower but
the time to actually come up with a
program is so much faster
essentially the libraries that I had on
the previous slide allow you to do these
sort of things for complicated finite
element solvers as well they provide you
with the building blocks and you can
just plug them together however you want
of course ultimately what it comes down
is this so if you plot it progress over
time for doing it yourself and using
existing software and you could plot
something like a straight red line for
whatever you write yourself because you
know your speed you know what what time
you have if you were to use somebody
else's code there
and there would be a learning curve
right in the beginning you would be much
slower and because you had to learn how
this whole system works but then it
comes a point where you become much
faster because you can use what you
understand is already in there and the
question of course is where that
crossover point is and I've been in this
field long enough and I've taught this
class and a number of times so I can
tell you that that crossover point is
that approximately two to four weeks if
you sit down as a student and all you do
is try to learn that software as opposed
to sit down and all you do is write your
own software then that takes you two to
four weeks before you get faster by
using something else than if you had to
write it yourself now if you think about
that the PhD takes three to four years
then you can immediately see how much
faster you would be if you used or how
much more you could achieve if you use
what other people have done so our
experience is that if you used these
existing libraries it's quite realistic
for example to have a PhD thesis that
contains or that that is based on a
program that works in - in 2d and 3d
uses complex geometries uses higher
order elements uses multi grid solvers
and preconditioners and so on and so
forth
if you did this from scratch it would
certainly take you ten or more years to
do this from a faculty perspective would
often hear is that colleagues tell me
that they want their students to
understand what they do and that's why
they let them write everything from
scratch and I think there is value to
this to a certain degree but that if you
know how quadrature works in 2d there's
really no weight why you need to learn
to do it again in 3d so the answer would
be let them write a toy code where they
understand how it works and then after
three months when they when they do know
how it works they throw it away and
start again based on some existing
software similar argument I hear is that
people say well you know I don't know if
these software's have packages have bugs
I know that you know I can trust my own
software I don't I don't have bugs in my
code the answer to this certainly is
while you can't be serious right I mean
we all make bugs of course your software
has bugs you delude yourself if you do
believe you that you don't but the real
answer of course is that the packages
that I've been talking about it that I
will talk about during the course of
this class are written by people who
have a lot of experience we have done
this for many years the software
packages have extensive test suits for
example do two runs approximately 2,700
2,700 tests after every single change to
the codebase and so you can believe that
there is a lot more let's say certainty
that there are fewer bugs in the
software again what you probably would
be able to do yourself so to conclude
this when you have to implement software
for a particular problem for example
because you want to develop new methods
or because you have a non-standard
problem really try to reuse what others
have done already there are many
high-quality open-source libraries that
do practically everything in scientific
computing and what you will find is that
you're far more productive that you will
be able to use state-of-the-art methods
and that your code will have far fewer
bugs than if you had to do it yourself
as a final pitch maybe if you're a
graduate student and you're watching
these classes one of the things that
have seen over and over again is that
because the time to come up with the
first version of the code is so short so
much shorter than if you had to write it
all yourself
you will get pictures very quickly and
invariably it impresses your adviser so
take that as one of the positive aspects
of this so with this I'll leave this
class you know or this lecture and we'll
cover all of the things that have talked
about in much more detail during the
rest of this semester this course and
I'll come back to many of these issues
at a later time
you